<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on raphaelite</title>
    <link>https://rapha.dev/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on raphaelite</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://rapha.dev/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Shrödinger&#39;s crouton</title>
      <link>https://rapha.dev/post/shrodingers-crouton/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rapha.dev/post/shrodingers-crouton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Until the 19th century, classical mechanics seemed to hold true for objects of all sizes, speeds and weights. Newton&amp;rsquo;s laws of gravitation and motion gave us the tools to explain and predict the movement of planets, comets, and even the tides. &lt;strong&gt;The accuracy of classical mechanics was held in simple formulas that seemed to represent our intuition&lt;/strong&gt;: objects attract each other proportionally to their weights, objects continue to move unless a force changes their movement. &lt;strong&gt;Newtonian physics was interpreted as evidence that humans were discovering laws of nature that existed independently of humanity&lt;/strong&gt;, and were ingrained in the world around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1859, astronomer Le Verrier, then director of the Paris observatory, reported that the movement of Mercury was slightly different than what Newtonian physics predicted: its orbit was shifting by a hundredth of a degree every century, a variation that could not be explained by the gravitational pull of known planets. &lt;strong&gt;We had found a first counter-example to Newtonian physics.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1915, Einstein&amp;rsquo;s theory of general relativity explained the slight shift in the Mercury orbit, and gave us a larger gravitational theory that superseded Newtonian physics. Yet its acceptance meant &lt;strong&gt;we had shifted from a version of the truth that was intuitive - time is a constant, objects pull each other proportionally to their weight - to one that was hard to imagine - space and time do not exist independently of matter&lt;/strong&gt;. Given that science was growing further apart from intuition, could we still trust our observations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the micro level, quantum mechanics had a similar effect: while it explained atomic interactions more accurately than classical physics, it was also much harder to grasp. The uncertainty principle implied that a unique, precise version of the truth could never be uncovered. The interpretation of light as both matter and energy feels esoteric to a classical mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://rapha.dev/images/dark_matter.png&#34; alt=&#34;dark_matter&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em style=&#34;
    position: relative;
    top: -20px;
    font-size: 14px;
&#34;&gt;source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com&#34;&gt;xkcd.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General relativity and quantum mechanics made science part ways with intuition. 20th century physics gave us &lt;strong&gt;more accurate models to explain our observations, yet paradoxically they are also a rebuttal of perception&lt;/strong&gt;. They posit that there is no universal measurement, no universal time, no universal truth. If the human experience doesn&amp;rsquo;t align with the scientific experience, should it be dismissed? Or are they both valid to a certain extent, just like light is neither pure matter nor pure energy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To predict and understand their environment, humans build thought patterns.&lt;/strong&gt; Since we all live on the same planet, we all experience time at the same rate, and so we are prone to believe that time is constant. Similarly, we found that general relativity is a good prediction model for our observation of planets, and adopted it among our many thought patterns. One day, we might find a counter-example to general relativity, and call it into question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical and mathematical thought patterns are singular through their intolerance towards counter-examples.&lt;/strong&gt; If you believe that herbal tea makes you less anxious, and tomorrow you find yourself jittery after a good cup of tea, your herbal belief might not falter. Yet a minor shift in the movement of one of the many astronomical bodies compared to what Newtonian physics predicts is enough to call into question a theory that had seemed true for centuries. Extreme susceptibility to counter-examples means that physical models often stand undefeated, and appear to be intrinsic to nature. The rigour of mathematics and physics is misleading: we end up believing that the world is a manifestation of our models, when our models are an (imperfect) representation of the world. &lt;strong&gt;Newton&amp;rsquo;s law did not exist until it was formulated in Newton&amp;rsquo;s brain.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adoption of general relativity is a welcome reminder that we cannot pretend to have found the laws of nature. It put our belief in the absoluteness of time in its right place - a thought pattern that is convenient for inhabitants of the same planet. &lt;strong&gt;Like matter and energy are both imperfect approximations of light, our thought patterns can only be imperfect approximations of nature.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Panacea Trap</title>
      <link>https://rapha.dev/post/the-panacea-trap/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rapha.dev/post/the-panacea-trap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;When all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a nail&amp;rdquo;. Yet we often strive to find the hammer, and make everything look like a nail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our environment is getting more complex, which means it&amp;rsquo;s also harder to grasp. At the same time, social media and on-demand video have decreased our attention span to less than that of a goldfish.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;strong&gt;We live in the perfect breeding-ground for simple, all-emcompassing theories.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether these theories are true is irrelevant. What makes their popularity is that they are compelling, reassuring, and easy to grasp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In software engineering, the perfect embodiment of this phenomenon is the turning of agile methodology into a dogma&lt;/strong&gt; that is followed by the letter. Attempting to remediate the failure of less flexible work methods that set details in advance, Agile embodies a more versatile approach that focuses on building the next step, and on adapting the product as more information comes to light. But as Agile became more popular, it turned into a large framework with its set of rules, priciples, and vocabulary. It was hailed as the response to all software problems. Your team of engineers is not delivering on time? Surely there&amp;rsquo;s an Agile rule they didn&amp;rsquo;t follow. The irony: Agile was created as a remedy to more rigid methodologies, and its followers turned it into an uncompromising panacea. &lt;strong&gt;Agile lacks agility in its own application.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In academia, the adopted paradigm is the p-value.&lt;/strong&gt; Driven by the temptation of judging all research using the same criteria, the academic world has chosen &amp;ldquo;p &amp;lt;= 0.05&amp;rdquo; has the one-size-fits-all rule for whether research is statistically significant or not. Consequently, researchers use p-hacking to find an assessment that is publishable, and those who refuse to use p-values don&amp;rsquo;t get published. Our attempt to narrow down the vast, complex problem of assessing research quality was foiled by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodhart&#39;s_law&#34;&gt;Goodhart&amp;rsquo;s law&lt;/a&gt;, and ran headfirst into the illusion that there is a metric to capture an overall subjective problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Both software engineering and academia are complex, hard to assess worlds that belong to tight-knit communities.&lt;/strong&gt; It makes them ripe to follow the latest trend en masse. They each chose paradigms without regards for whether they are useful or true, but rather because the chosen paradigms are compelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about politics? You were waiting for that one surely. Good policies are hard to define or measure, and political parties are built around partisanship, so &lt;strong&gt;the political world is ripe for adoption of panacea&lt;/strong&gt;. That panacea might be small government, the fight against immigration, or against inequality. Not enough jobs? Migrants. Too much taxes? Migrants. A measles outbreak? You got it. Instead of looking into potential causes and solutions for individual problems, politics is dominated by panacea crusaders who picked their hammer and are thirsty for nails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aquinas famously said: &amp;ldquo;fear the man of a single book&amp;rdquo;. Little did he know that the man of a thousand mobile apps would inherit the same flaws.&lt;/strong&gt; We have access to a broader range of information than ever before. It&amp;rsquo;s disappointing that this easier, cheaper access to broad knowledge didn&amp;rsquo;t come with more prudence when we formulate theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://internet.psych.wisc.edu/wp-content/uploads/532-Master/532-UnitPages/Unit-09/Attention_Goldfish_Abbreviated.pdf&#34;&gt;https://internet.psych.wisc.edu/wp-content/uploads/532-Master/532-UnitPages/Unit-09/Attention_Goldfish_Abbreviated.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>